"Eliminating Heart Disease,
the Number One Cause of Death"
Heart disease is
the leading cause of death
in the United States,
and has been
our number one killer
every single year
for more than a century.
Dr. William Clifford Roberts
published extensively
on the cause of our top killer.
He was the Chief of Pathology
at the National Institutes
of Health for 30 years
before he headed up
Baylor University's
Heart and Vascular Institute.
He authored more than
1,300 scientific publications,
wrote more than a hundred
book chapters on cardiology,
and was the editor-in-chief
of The American Journal
of Cardiology for 40 years.
Well, what is the cause
of atherosclerosis?
Well, first of all,
didn't he mean causes?
I mean, there are
lots of things
that can increase
our risk of heart disease:
high blood pressure,
diabetes, cigarette smoking,
inactivity, obesity.
But none of that matters,
he said,
unless we have
high cholesterol.
Atherosclerosis is
a cholesterol problem.
Yes, these other factors
can amplify
the cholesterol damage,
but as long as cholesterol
levels are low enough,
heart disease remains rare.
There's only one necessary
risk factor for atherosclerosis,
and that's elevated cholesterol
in the blood.
How low does our cholesterol
have to be
to prevent and arrest
atherosclerotic plaques?
Ideally, our bad cholesterol,
the LDL,
should be under 70 milligrams
per deciliter,
which is less than
1.8 millimole per liter.
"If such a goal was created,
the great scourge
of the Western world would be
essentially eliminated."
So, we could put
a hundred million people
on a lifetime of sufficient
cholesterol-lowering drugs
or be what he called
a "pure vegetarian fruit eater,"
which is how he referred
to those eating whole food,
plant-based diets.
Now, if we put everyone
on drugs,
millions would suffer
side effects,
such as developing diabetes,
so, of course
a plant-based diet
"is the least expensive
and safest means
of achieving
the plaque-preventing LDL goal,
but few in the Western world
are willing
to live on the herbivore diet."
Because, according to, probably,
the most renowned cardiovascular
pathologist of all time,
the number one cause
of our number one killer
is elevated cholesterol,
which means the cause
of our number one killer
is not eating enough plants.